{"tossups": [{"question": "In 2017, this state\u2019s town of Cleveland settled a 52-year-long court case about the segregation of its public schools. This state passed a law banning felons from college admission, then charged a black applicant with false voter registration and convicted him<em> in absentia</em> on the same day. Ultimately, Robert F. Kennedy ordered U.S. Marshals to desegregate this state\u2019s flagship university on the request of Governor Ross Barnett, who refused to do it without being coerced. For ten points, name this US state where James Meredith attended college in Oxford.", "answer": "<b> Mississippi</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One side in this war benefited from trees planted as target markers years prior by a spy in the Ministry of Defense. The losing side in this war renewed its commitment to \u201cno peace\u201d and \u201cno negotiation\u201d in the Khartoum Resolution. This war began with Operation Focus, a surprise attack that crippled the losing side\u2019s air force, contributing to that side\u2019s loss of the Sinai Peninsula and the Golan Heights. For ten points, name this 1967 war, a quick victory for Israel over an Arab coalition.", "answer": "<b> Six-Day</b> War (accept<b> Third Arab-Israeli</b> War; accept<b> 1967 Arab-Israeli</b> War before\u201c1967\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Members of this group collaborated on an unfinished opera-ballet about the Polabian Slavs in the 10th century titled<em> Mlada</em>. An 1185 campaign against the Cumans and their Khans is the subject of an opera from this group that features the Polovtsian Dances; another work from this group is about the fall of the Rurikids. The composers of<em> Prince Igor</em> and<em> Boris Godunov</em>, Alexander Borodin and Modest Mussorgsky, were members of, for ten points, what nationalist movement in 19th century Russian music?", "answer": "The<b> Mighty Handful</b> (accept the Mighty<b> Five</b>; accept Moguchaya<b> kuchka</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This man recognized the authority of Philip Augustus over Angevin lands in the Treaty of Le Goulet, but later tried to challenge those claims in the disastrous Battle of Bouvines [boo-veen]. This man was excommunicated by Innocent III after refusing to allow Stephen Langton be appointed Archbishop of Canterbury. This king was cornered at Runnymede by discontented barons, forcing this man to curb his own power to tax and promise trials by jury. For ten points, name this English king who signed the Magna Carta.", "answer": "King<b> John</b> (accept<b> John</b> I; accept<b> John</b> Lackland)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This politician was accused of taking bribes from the Union Pacific Railroad in the Mulligan Letters. This politician was endorsed in a speech by Robert Ingersoll, leading to him being nicknamed the \u201cPlumed Knight.\u201d This politician lost the support of many Catholics when a pastor denounced Democrats as the party of \u201cRum, Romanism, and Rebellion\u201d. For ten points, name this senator and so-called \u201cContinental Liar\u201d from Maine who was defeated by Grover Cleveland in the election of 1884.", "answer": "James G.<b> Blaine</b> Page 1", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A king of this location was believed to have invented the chariot to hide his serpentine feet. Ericthonius ruled this location, as did another serpent-legged king named Cecrops, who judged an olive tree to be better than a salt water spring. Another king of this city died when his son returned with black sails on his boat after slaying the Minotaur. The mythological figures Theseus and Aegeus ruled, for ten points, what ancient Greek city whose origin myth includes Poseidon losing a contest to be its namesake?", "answer": "<b> Athens</b> (accept<b> Attica</b> before \u201ccity\u201d is read)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "Participants in this event were captured at Arthur Allen\u2019s home, which became known as its leader\u2019s\u201cCastle.\u201d This event was sparked by a Doeg raid on the farm of Thomas Matthews. The namesake of this event issued a Declaration of the People and massacred the Occoneechee people. John Ingram replaced the leader of this event after he died of dysentery. Governor William Berkley hung 23 men for participation in, for ten points, what 1676 rebellion that led to the burning of Jamestown?", "answer": "<b> Bacon\u2019s</b> Rebellion", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s namesake stand was a cast iron base used to keep his subject still. This man, who depicted an elderly Andrew Jackson at his estate and created portraits of Edgar Allan Poe, used the albumen print technique after originally working with daguerreotypes. Ulysses S. Grant places his hand on a tree in a work by, for ten points, what artist whose exhibition<em> The Dead of Antietam</em> displayed the gruesome nature of the Civil War via photography?", "answer": "Mathew<b> Brady</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This man signaled his newfound status by changing his last name to include \u201cNovyi.\u201d Enemies of this man accused him of joining the Khlysty sect. This man was lured into the Moika Palace on the night of his downfall, and when he drank Felix Yusupov\u2019s cyanide-laced wine without any effect, he was shot three times. This man had gained royal influence due to his apparent ability to stop the bleeding of Alexei, the hemophiliac heir of the tsar. For ten points, name this Russian mystic who advised Nicholas II.", "answer": "Grigori<b> Rasputin</b> Page 2", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "One of these events probably killed Union soldier Boston Corbett, the man who shot John Wilkes Booth. Wisconsin\u2019s Green Island Lighthouse had to be kept on during the day during one of these events that may have been caused by fragments of Comet Biela. Peshtigo was struck by one of these events on the same day that one began on DeKoven Street, possibly after a cow kicked over a lantern. For ten points, name this type of natural disaster that destroyed thousands of wooden houses in Chicago in 1871.", "answer": "<b> fire</b>s (accept additional information, like the Great Peshtigo<b> Fire</b> or Great Chicago<b> Fire</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This empire used the paiza seal to indicate officials authorized to use the stations of the Yam supply route. This empire conquered the Kingdom of Dali and installed a local governor known as a Tusi [tu-szu]. This empire was betrayed by its vassal, the Western Xia, and it finished one conquest at the Battle of Yamen on the Pearl River Delta. After crossing the Yangtze, this empire was able to defeat the Southern Song Dynasty. For ten points, name this empire that conquered China under the rule of Genghis and Kublai Khan.", "answer": "<b> Mongol</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Generals for this city included Sebastiano Venier and Agostino Barbargio, who both fought against the Ottomans in the Battle of Lepanto. The word \u201cghetto\u201d originated from this city, which was attacked by Pope Julius II\u2019s League of Cambrai. A ring was annually dropped into the water in this city\u2019s Marriage of the Sea ceremony, which was overseen by its doge. For ten points, name this \u201cMost Serene Republic,\u201dan Italian city-state known for its many canals.", "answer": "<b> Venice</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "His forces were excommunicated because they sacked Zara, even before they attacked Constantinople.", "answer": "Enrico<b> Dandolo</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Mirabel was unpopular because it is a decidedly long drive away from the island in the Saint Lawrence River on which this city was built.", "answer": "<b> Montreal</b> <b></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b>According to legend, because a ruler of this empire asked for the head of the Maharaja of Zabag, the ruler\u2019s head was instead taken by the Maharaja. Rajendra Chola helped this</b> <b>empire defeat the Tambralinga Kingdom and the Srivijayas in the (+)</b> <b>11th century. The</b> <b>Baphuon temple and Baray water resevoirs were built by this empire. The diplomat Zhou Daguan was sent to this empire, traveling through (*) </b> Tonle Sap lake. Several kings named Jayavarman ruled, for ten points, what empire that built Angkor Wat in what is now Cambodia?", "answer": "<b> Khmer</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This group was criticized for employing the Gehlen Organization in launching Operation Bohemia, where a Czech detonator was successfully secured. This group\u2019s leader, William Colby, helped compile a set of documents known as the \u201cFamily Jewels\u201d that detailed their</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>assassination efforts. Carlos Armas was supported by this group during Operation</b> <b>PBSUCCESS, in which the United Fruit Company convinced this group to (*)</b> launch a coup d\u2019etat in Guatemala. Allen Dulles once led, for ten points, what American foreign intelligence service?", "answer": "<b> Central Intelligence Agency</b> (or<b> CIA</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>Clement VII contradicted Catholic canon law by mourning the sack of Rome with one of these objects, creating a fashion that lasted for successive popes. Grace Bedell suggested</b> <b>the use of this object. Walter Hawkins published an 1845 paper about a (+)</b> <b>tax on these</b> <b>objects, for which a token was given after the tax was paid. Flemish painter Anthony (*) </b>van Dyck popularized a style of this fashion, and Peter the Great passed a tax on boyars who chose to wear them. For ten points, name this fashion choice that Abraham Lincoln was inspired to adopt because\u201call the ladies like whiskers.\u201d", "answer": "<b> beard</b>s (accept<b> facial hair</b> in general, but do not accept mustache; prompt on \u201cvan Dyck\u201dafter \u201cFlemish\u201d is read) (4) <b>This philosopher, who described a compound of matter and form which he termed</b> <em><b>hylomorphism</b></em><b>, divided tragic theater into elements such as</b><em><b> opsis</b></em><b>,</b><em><b> mythos</b></em><b>, and</b><em><b> ethos</b></em><b> in what is believed to be the first work of (+) literary theory. This philosopher fled Athens in 323 BC after the death of his patron king. (*)</b><em> Poetics</em>,<em> Metaphysics</em>, and the<em> Nicomachean Ethics</em> were written by, for ten points, what Greek philosopher, a student of Plato who tutored Alexander the Great? ANSWER:<b> Aristotle</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>A film produced during this war depicts a leader who is jailed by Marcas the blacksmith. The Hello Girls operated in this war, as did the farmerettes. During this war, a mysterious</b> <b>explosion that was suspected to be sabotage occurred at (+)</b> <b>Black Tom Island. Charles</b> <b>Lathrop Pack ran a War Garden Commission in this war, for which \u201cwheatless Wednesdays\u201dand \u201cmeatless Tuesdays\u201d were created. The (*) </b> Zimmerman Telegram helped push the U.S. to declare war in, for ten points, what war in which the lost propaganda film<em> The Kaiser, the Beast of Berlin</em> was produced?", "answer": "<b> World War I</b> Page 9", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This leader defeated the Helvetii at the Battle of Bibracte and the Nervii at the Battle of the Sabis. This man, who was rumored to have had an affair with King Nicomedes</b> <b>in his youth, was once captured by a group of (+)</b> <b>in his youth, was once captured by a group of (+)</b> <b>pirates who he later had crucified.</b> <b>Vercingetorix was defeated at the siege of (*)</b> Alesia by this man, who legendarily declared \u201cthe Alesia by this man, who legendarily declared \u201cthe die is cast\u201d upon crossing the Rubicon to instigate a civil war. For ten points, name this Roman dictator who was assassinated by conspirators on the Ides of March.", "answer": "Gaius<b> Julius Caesar</b> (prompt on Caesar)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>Controversies flared over the necessity of HOM, PP, and IT redactions in this document. After the release of this document, Jerry Nadler subpoenaed a former White House Counsel to testify before the House Judiciary Committee. (+) Kellyanne Conway called for apologies in the wake of this document, whose redacted form was published by Attorney General William (*) </b> Barr. Rod Rosenstein commissioned this document after Jeff Sessions recused himself in 2017. For ten points, name this Special Council investigation report prepared by a former FBI director concerning Russian interference in the 2016 election.", "answer": "<b> Mueller Report</b> (accept<b> Report on the Investigation into Russian Interference in the 2016 Presidential Election</b>; prompt on descriptions related to that document\u2019s title) (8) <b>This man\u2019s relationship with Catalina Ju\u00b4arez infuriated her brother, Diego Vel\u00b4azquez</b> <b>de Cu\u00b4ellar, until he finally married her. This man assembled troops to fight against the</b> <b>expedition of Panfilo de (+)</b> <b>Narvaez while a small detachment under Pedro Alvarado was</b> <b>Narvaez while a small detachment under Pedro Alvarado was</b> <b>left behind and massacred during La (*)</b> <b>left behind and massacred during La (*)</b> Noche Triste. This man benefited from an alliance with Tlaxcala [t\u2019lahsh-ca-LA] and the work of the translator La Malinche [mah-leen-chay] in his campaign against Montezuma. For ten points, name this conquistador who defeated the Aztec Empire. ANSWER: Hern\u00b4an<b> Cort\u00b4es</b>  (1) <b>An ill-fated defensive maneuver during this campaign prompted its leader to</b> <b>remark \u201cIf he will go to the Ohio River, I\u2019ll give him rations.\u201d Men recruited to forcibly take goods from civilians during this campaign were referred to as \u201cbummers.\u201dThe leader of this campaign had (+) railroads twisted into what became known as his</b> <b>namesake \u201cneckties.\u201d At the endpoint of this campaign, its leader sent (*)</b> Abraham Lincoln a telegram offering a Christmas gift of the captured city of Savannah. For ten points, name this scorched earth campaign that devastated Georgia during the Civil War. ANSWER: William Tecumseh Sherman\u2019s<b> March to the Sea</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}